this is barry's alma
zelma on insurance
today it's time to speak about the
doctrine of ubarime
fidei
or
in english utmost good faith
insurance is a business
that requires that the parties to the
contract of insurance
act ethically and with utmost good faith
ethics is a process
of systematically applying
using defending and recommending
concepts
of right and wrong
behavior ethical behavior
is
always required of both parties to a
contract of insurance
for the system of insurance to work
if any party to the insurance contract
acts unethically
the ability of insurance to work
effectively
to provide the indemnity promised by the
policies
and to
be profitable
will fail
ethics
is therefore
the essence of insurance
since insurance was first created
back in ancient sumeria alongside the
tigris and euphrates rivers
it has been a business of utmost good
faith
as a result the insured and the insurer
are expected to treat each other
ethically
insurance was created to spread the risk
from individuals to multitudes
spreading the risk in a fair
ethical and honorable manner
from one person to many is the basis
upon which a system of insurance was
founded
the insurance contract since
modern insurance was first created
was founded on the concept of ubereme
fidei
the latin phrase uberebe fide
is used to express the principle
that a contract of insurance must be
made in perfect good faith
with neither the insurer nor the insured
concealing anything from the other
in the case of insurance
both the insured and the insurer must
observe
the most perfect good faith towards each
other so that the insurer
understands the risk it is asked to take
and the insured understands the risks
accepted by the insurer
insurers and reinsurers those who insure
the insurer
are dependent on utmost good faith which
may be viewed as a legal rule but also
as a tradition
honored by
insurers and seating insurers and
reinsurers
in their ongoing commercial
relationships
ubereme fite has its
roots in british
jurisprudence
the doctrine has historically been
applied to all insurance contracts
issued in or to be performed in the
united states
the doctrine of utmost good faith
was stated by the u.s supreme court
dating back to
1828 in a case called mcclanahan versus
universal insurance
several federal cases
have applied the duty of ubereme fidei
in the marine insurance setting
applying the doctrine more strictly than
in property casualty life health or
disability insurance
under marine insurance
that's insurance of vessels going across
wide spans of water like the oceans and
the great lakes
under marine insurance's interpretation
of uber rime fide
any failure to disclose a material fact
not known by the underwriter
that is or should be
within the knowledge of the insured
party is grounds for rescission of the
policy even if the omission or
misstatement
is the result of the insured's mistake
an accident
the insurance forgetfulness
any of those grounds
if it deceives the insurer is grounds
for rescission
in the marine setting
the insured is required to disclose
everything that is material to the
insurer
even if the insurer does not ask
not all federal circuit courts apply the
uber aim a feed a doctrine to marine
insurance policies
but most do
the doctrine of uberme fide
the highest degree of good faith
provides that failure by the insured to
disclose conditions affecting the risk
of which he is aware
makes the contract voidable at the
insurers option
insurance policies
traditionally contracts ubereme fee day
and a failure by the insurer to disclose
conditions affecting the risk of which
he is aware
makes the contract voidable at the
option of the insurer
similarly misrepresentation or
concealment of material fact
by the insurer
allows the insured to declare the
contract void
at the insured's option
that is because
the duty to treat each other fairly and
in good faith is mutual
the majority of courts
faced with the application of uber rime
fide to a marine insurance policy
have found that utmost good faith
applies
insurance cannot operate
it cannot exist
profitably
or even
to work at all
without the ethical doctrine of ubereme
feeding
under the doctrine of
uberever up knows good faith
the insured in a maritime insurance
contract is required
required to disclose to the insurer all
known circumstances
that materially affect the insurer's
risk
the default of which renders the
insurance contract voidable
the parties to a marine insurance policy
must accord each other
the highest degree of good faith
this duty of good faith requires the
insured to disclose to the insurer
all known circumstances that materially
affect the risk being insured
because the insured is in the best
position to know of any facts that may
be material to the wrist the insured is
obligated
obligated by the doctrine of good faith
to disclose those facts to the insurer
regardless of whether the insurer makes
a specific inquiry about the facts
for example if the owner of a vessel
knows that its captain
is an
alcoholic who may be drunk at any time
when the ship is
being set upon the sea
must disclose that fact to the insurer
and if
it isn't disclosed the insurer can void
the policy
similarly if
the ship
has
a bilge pump that doesn't work and is
taking in water
and that fact is not
disclosed to the insurer
the insured has breached ubereme fidei
and the insurer can
declare the policy void
the doctrine reflects an enlightened
moral policy
based on the presumption that the party
procuring insurance
is not in possession of any facts
material to the risk which he does not
disclose
indeed it is the duty of the insured to
place the underwriter
in the same situation as himself
an insured who conceals or misrepresents
a material fact
commits fraud which avoids the policy
and is a clear breach
of the ethical obligation of the insured
fraud is an obvious breach of the
contract
and the implied covenant of good faith
and fair dealing
because of material misrepresentation
made with knowledge provided to an
insurer with an intent to deceive the
insurer
that
effectively deceives the insurer to its
detriment
is
fraud under common law understanding
of what fraud is
it is the ethical obligation of the
insured
to truthfully
and fully advise the insurer of the risk
the insured is asking the insurer to
take
failure to do so
even if there was no intent to deceive
is sufficient to allow the insurer to
rescind the policy
if the insurer was actually deceived
in some instances
the law chokes on the issue of ethics in
good faith
it is sometimes difficult for a court to
determine
which of the two considerations
influences the classification of
insurance contracts
at least the insurance considerations
have been referred to as ubereme fidei
in england and in the united states
the two countries however
are not necessarily in accord in their
interpretation
of
ubereme fidei
nothing
is better established in the law of
marine insurance
that a mistake or commission
material to a marine risk
whether it be willful or accidental
or result from mistake negligence or
voluntary ignorance avoids the policy
concealment in the law of marine
insurance
is the failure to disclose any material
factor circumstance in relation to the
subject matter of the contract which may
increase the liability's loss
or affect the risk
or obligation assumed and which is in
fact or law within
or ought to be
within the knowledge of one party and of
which the other party had no actual or
presumptive knowledge
in the case of marine insurance
the insured must disclose all facts
material to the risk
and in default of such duty the contract
may be avoided by the insurer the policy
never attaches to the risk and is void
for the reason that the risk assumed
is not the one intended to be assumed by
the parties
this was quintero versus geico marine a
2019 decision
of the third circuit court of appeal
in the leading english case of carter
versus beam
decided in the house of lords in 1766
lord mansfield declared that even an
innocent concealment of a material fact
made the contract voidable
saying that the
question therefore must always be
whether there was under all
circumstances at the time the policy was
underwritten
a fair representation or a concealment
fraudulent if designed or though not
designed varying materially
the object of the policy
and changing the risk understood to be
run
the doctrine of ubereme fidei obligates
the assured
to volunteer information which might
have a bearing on the scope of the risk
assumed
and the failure to do so
will allow the insurer to avoid the
policy this video was adapted from my
book ethics for the insurance
professional second edition
which is available as both a kindle book
and a paperback from
amazon.com
if you found this video to be
interesting or useful to you and your
colleagues please pass it on it's free
and please also subscribe to my rumble
channel
and click on
the rumble button if you think the video
was worth your effort
my youtube channel
my blog and my sub stack publications
so that you can be advised of future
videos
and future blog postings
thank you for your attention